Guide to the Pool Family Papers, 1930-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Photographs and Artwork, 1930s-1990s, (5 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
  Materials in the Photographs and Artwork series include both professional photographs from the Division of Visual Education at the Foreign Missions Board of the Southern Baptist Convention, along with personal portraits and snapshots taken by the Pools of both family and Nigerian scenes. The family snapshots are loosely sorted into Pool Family and Nigerian subseries, but have not been arranged further. They contain a range of dates and subjects, including the NBTS, Mt. Nimba, scenes of Nigerian and Liberian culture and festivals, travel photographs, and more formal portraits of friends and family members. Many of these photographs have been captioned by Jim Pool. Box 14 includes a small photograph album of Pool family vacation photographs. Boxes 16 and 17 contain the FMB photographs, which include both Nigerian and Liberian churches, pastors, parishioners, and scenes of local life in Africa. Most include detailed captions. The artwork present in this series consists of a set of watercolor prints with scenes of Liberia, created by Swedish artist Roland Svensson and published in 1969. It has been housed in Oversize Folder 1.
  - Pool family photo pages, removed from album (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Pool family glass negative [broken] (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Pool family photograph album, 1930s-1940s (Box 14)
  - Pool family, general (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Pool family, 1970s (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Pool family and friends, 1974-1985 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Pool family: photographs taken by Jim in Nigeria, U.S.A., and Rome (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Nigerian photographs (Box 15, Folder 5-7)
  - FMB color photographs, 8 images (Box 16)
  - FMB color photographs, 10 images (Box 17)
  - "Liberia" watercolor prints, by Roland Svensson, 1969 (Opaperfolder 1)
- Family Writings, 1930-1998, (6 boxes)
  The Family Writings series consists of non-correspondence writings and notes by the Pool family and their relatives. It ranges from 1930-1998 and is divided into five subseries: J.C. Pool Autobiographical Materials, J.C. Pool Sermon Notes and Writings, Elizabeth Pool Writings, E.C. Routh Writings, and Other Pool Family Writings, with this last reserved for writings by family members other than J.C. Pool, Elizabeth Pool, and E.C. Routh. In addition to these subseries, the collection contains a small amount of writings and poems collected but not authored by the Pools.
  The J.C. Pool Sermon Notes and Writings subseries is comprised of J.C. Pool’s early notes and publications while a student at the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, including his doctoral thesis on the Jesuits, “An Estimate of the Society of Jesus in the Reformation and the Post-Reformation Periods”; dated sermons, sermon notes, and writings, including his address at his father’s funeral, writings on Yoruba culture and religion, a history of the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary co-written with Elizabeth Pool, various lectures given at commencements, graduations, and conferences, as well as one broadcast on Nigerian radio, and another essay on the history of the NBTS; a number of sermon notes and Bible Study lesson plans during the Pools’ tenure at Mount Nimba Baptist Church in Yekepa, Liberia from May 1971-July 1972; two collections of typed sermons, the latter of which focuses especially on Christianity in Africa; and a significant amount of undated material, largely handwritten sermon notes.
  The J.C. Pool Autobiographies subseries has two types of material. The first consists of manuscript drafts of J.C. Pool’s autobiography, both typed and handwritten, covering the years 1905-1951. The second consists of diaries and handwritten summaries from 1935-1972 (non-inclusive), with diaries from 1942 and 1943.
  The Elizabeth Pool Writings subseries consists of notes and writings by Elizabeth Pool, including a brief autobiographical sketch, notes for her 1951 biography of Lucille Reagan for the Foreign Mission Board, a copy of an article she contributed to a local book on the history of the Grapevine region circa 1982, and various poems and essays, as well as a draft of her book A Hill Called Moon circa 1943.
  The E.C. Routh Writings subseries consists of notes and writings by Elizabeth Pool’s father, E.C. Routh, who was the editor of and a contributing writer to the Baptist Messenger. The collection includes essay drafts, sermon notes, and biographical sketches of both personal friends and prominent Baptists.
  The Other Writings subseries includes work by Alice Routh (E.C. Routh’s wife and Elizabeth Pool’s mother), J.C. and Elizabeth’s son Jim and daughter Carolyn, and other Pool relations. Stories, poems, biographies, and essays are all present.
  - J.C. Pool Sermon Notes and Writings
    - Greek Notes; Introductory-Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1930; Luke Gospel, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - "Missionary Element in Isaiah," 1932-1933 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Doctoral thesis, SBTS, 1934-1935 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - 1932-1956 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - c. 1942 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - c. 1945-1950 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - 1965-1977 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Mt. Nimba Baptist Church, Yekepa, Liberia, Bible Study, 1971 Aug.-1972 Mar. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Mt. Nimba Baptist Church, Yekepa, Liberia, 1971 Aug. 1972 July (Box 19, Folder 3-7)
    - Collection of sermons, 1957-1970 and undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Collection of sermons focusing on Africa, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, including: essays on missionary work, hunting in Africa, notes and packing lists, NBTS work, family history, etc. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Undated (Box 20, Folder 5-8)
    - Undated (Box 21, Folder 1-8)
    - Undated (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - J.C. Pool Autobiographies
    - Manuscripts, 1905-1934 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Manuscripts, 1935-1937 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Manuscripts, 1938-1944, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Notes and diaries, 1935-1945 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Notes, 1946-1972 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Elizabeth Pool Writings
    - Go-to-Africa gift list, wedding gift list, and French grammar notes (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 1934-1995 and undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Partial draft of autobiographical book, 1942-1943 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - A Hill Called Moon draft, 1943 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - E.C. Routh Writings
    - 1935-1960 and undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Sermon notes, 1950s (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Biographical sketches of friends and prominent Baptists, 1950s (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Other Writings
    - Other Pool family writings, 1935-1995 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Jim Pool's art and schoolwork, 1951-1995 and undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Writings and poems collected by the Pool family, 1935-1998 and undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
- J.C. Pool Teaching Materials, 1948-1970, (1 box)
  The J.C. Pool Teaching Materials series consists of materials used by J.C. Pool throughout his career as an educator, as well as student papers written for him at the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary. Syllabi, lesson plans, notes, and exam materials cover a range of classes, with a large portion of the material devoted to courses on Christian missions. The NBTS student papers focus on the interaction of Christian theology and Yoruba cultural and religious practices.
  - Syllabi, lesson plans, and exam materials, 1948-1955 and undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi, lesson plans, and exam materials, 1967 and undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - "Missions" syllabi and lesson plans, 1966-1967 and undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - NBTS student papers, 1945-1967 and undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - "Special" NBTS student papers, 1967-1970 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Christian theology NBTS papers, 1969 May (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - "Major Theological Issues as Viewed through Traditional Yoruba Thought," NBTS student papers, 1969-1970 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - NBTS student thesis, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - "History of Baptist Missions" by H.C. Coorner (Box 24, Folder 9)
- Travel Records and Memorabilia, 1934-1991, (1 box)
  The Travel Records and Memorabilia series contains records of the Pool family’s various trips from 1934 to 1991, with some undated material. The series includes an itinerary summarizing nearly all of the journeys documented in the rest of the series. It also includes material such as luggage tags, programs from events held during various cruises, airplane tickets and records, printed travel books, and postcards and other tourist materials. Notable journeys that receive a significant amount of coverage include Elizabeth Pool’s 1979 journey to Nigeria for longtime friend Osad Imasogie’s inauguration as Principal of the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary in Ogbomosho.
  - Legal documents re: travel, immigration (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - 1930s-1940s (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - 1958 July (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - 1958 Aug.-1960 July (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - 1970 July and 1972 June (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Itineraries, 1934-1972 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Lamco Yekepa, Liberia, tourist material and postcards (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Elizabeth Pool's trip to Nigeria for Osad Imasogie's inauguration, 1979-1980 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Postcards, general (Box 25, Folder 11)
- Missionary Materials, 1938-1980, (3 boxes)
  The Missionary Materials series largely consists of records from the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary and related organizations including the Nigerian Baptist Mission, the American Baptist Mission, the Christian Council of Nigeria, the Baptist Mission of Nigeria, and the Home and Foreign Mission Board of the Southern Baptist Convention. It ranges from 1938-1980 with some undated material. In addition to general policies and proceedings, the material touches on polygamy and marriage practices in the 1930s-1950s, Nigerianization, and questions concerning refugees and relief efforts during and after the Nigerian Civil War (1967-1970).
  This series contains three sorts of materials: agendas and meeting minutes, reports, and founding documents. Agendas and meeting minutes contains materials from the organizations listed above and is arranged chronologically, not by organization; issues covered in this material include budgets, personnel, education and schools (including enrollment and accreditation issues), medical facilities, agriculture, transportation, media (use of AV equipment, literature, publishing, and bookstores), and scholarships. Reports mostly contains materials by or about the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, including yearly histories and information about budgets, enrollments, and calendars. Founding documents consist of resolutions, statements of purpose, constitutions, personnel policies, manuals, and programs for the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, the Western Division of the Baptist Mission of Nigeria, the Ogbomosho Baptist Medical Center, and the Foreign Mission Board. Other materials include catalogs, directories, issues of The Theologue (a student publication), and 1970 press materials from the Foreign Mission Board.
  - Agendas and meetings minutes, 1938-1951 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Agendas and meeting minutes, 1940s (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Agendas and meeting minutes, 1950s (2 folders) (Box 35, Folder 5-6)
  - Agendas and meetings minutes, 1952-1959 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Agendas and meetings minutes, 1960-1964 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Agendas and meeting minutes, 1960's (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Agendas and meetings minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Agendas and meeting minutes, 1970's and Undated (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Agendas and meetings minutes, 1976-1979 and undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Founding documents, 1954-1980 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Foreign Mission Board materials, 1930s-1970s (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - NBTS The Theologue issues, 1958 July and 1962 Mar. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Student catalogues, 1956-1965 and undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Speeches and addresses, 1947 and 1979 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Speeches and addresses, 1964-1970 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Directories, 1969 and 1980 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 1945-1977 and undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Reports, 1947-1968 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Reports, Undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Baptist Schools, 1940s (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Baptist Schools, 1950s (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Baptist Schools, 1960s (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 35, Folder 9)
- Family Papers, 1930s-1990s, (4 boxes)
  The Family Papers Series contains family history and genealogy notes; awards, diplomas, and other honors acquired by the Pools throughout their lives; family legal and financial documents, such as receipts, licenses, debt records, and property inventories; and other miscellaneous items including a family guest book, cancelled stamps from throughout the world, and other items saved by the Pools. The bulk of this series consists of memorial materials from J.C. Pool's death and funeral.
  - Family history (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Financial records relating to C. Routh's debts in Lake Charles, LA, 1950-1951 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Financial records (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Property inventories and lists (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Awards, degrees, and honors (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Legal records (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - J.C. Pool memorial album (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - J.C. Pool memorial binder 1, Jan. 1978 (Box 32, Folder 2-4)
  - J.C. Pool memorial binder 2 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - J.C. Pool memorial binder 3 (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
  - J.C. Pool memorial binder 3 (Box 33, Folder 1-4)
  - J.C. Pool memorial notebook (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - J.C. Pool memorial papers, 1977 Oct.-1978 July (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - J.C. Pool memorial papers, from Notebook 1, 1978 Jan. (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - J.C. Pool memorial papers, from Notebook 2, 1978 Jan. (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - J.C. Pool memorial papers, notices of gifts and donations, 1978 Jan. (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Other Pool family memorial materials, 1966-1987 and undated (Box 33, Folder 10)
- Printed Materials, 1930s-1990s, (3 boxes)
  The Printed Materials series is comprised of published materials collected by the Pool family and ranges from the 1930s to the 1990s with some undated material. It is divided into five subseries: Clippings, Programs and Publications, Reports, Magazines, and Books. Clippings consists of clipped materials from magazines and newspapers, as well as a few complete editions. It mostly contains articles and notices about the Pools from local papers (weddings, visits, obituaries, etc.); it also contains some examples of published writing by the Pools and their relatives, particularly columns by Elizabeth Pool’s father, E.C. Routh. Programs and Publications contains a large number of church bulletins and programs, many from the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary and the First Baptist Church Oke’lerin (both in Ogbomosho, Nigeria), and others from various services attended by the Pools. It also includes other published materials, such as religious and travel pamphlets, as well as small New Testaments and other books owned by the Pools and their relatives. Magazines includes a variety of publications collected by the Pools, most of which are missionary publications (Home and Foreign Fields, World Comrades, Tell, SIMNOW), general interest Nigerian publications (Ibadan, Nigeria Magazine), or religious and educational publications from the United States (Review and Expositor, The OBU Report, Baptist Messenger, Founders Campaign Quarterly). There are generally only one or two issues of each magazine, with one exception: a significant portion of this subseries consists of issues of The Nigerian Baptist from 1954-1988 (non-inclusive). Reports consists almost entirely of various published reports on Nigerian politics and government. The Books subseries contains printed publications, written in both the English and Yoruba languages. Many of these books include notes or inscriptions by the Pools.
  - Clippings
    - Clippings, 1930s (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1940s (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1950s (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1960s (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1970s (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1980s (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Clippings, 1990s and undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Programs and Publications
    - Programs and Publications, 1930s-1940s (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Programs and Publications, 1950s (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Programs and Publications, 1960s (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Programs and Publications, 1970s (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Programs and Publications, 1978-1979 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Programs and Publications, 1980s-1990s (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Programs and Publications, undated (Box 30, Folder 4-7)
  - Magazines
    - Re: Missionary work, 1934, 1935, 1969, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Re: Nigeria, general, 1960 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Re: Nigeria, general, 1960 (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Re: Nigeria, general, 1962-1968 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - The Nigerian Baptist, 1954-1968 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - The Nigerian Baptist, 1969-1982 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - The Nigerian Baptist, 1983-1988 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Re: United States, religious and educational (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Reports
    - Reports, 1939-1955 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Reports, 1957-1969 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Books
    - Iwe Kika Ekarun Li Ede Yoruba (1947) (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - The History of the Yorubas: From the Earliest Times to the Beginning of the British Protectorate (1966) (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Really Free! The News Kwacha Freedom Uhuru (1966) (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - How to be Nigerian (1967) (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Baptist Missions in Nigeria (1928) (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Iwe Itan Ogbomoso (1934) (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - IFA (Undated) (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Owe Yoruba At' Ebo (Undated) (Box 34, Folder 11)